in this video we are going to create a
grid visualization using a custom Shader
and we are going to place it on top of
our plane where we want to be placing
our objects to create our grid
visualization we need to use a custom
Shader and to do that we need to import
the Shader graph package so go to the
top menu window and select the package
manager here in the top left corner we
are going to select the unity registry
from our list and in the top right
corner in the search box we are going to
type Shader
and now you should see the Shader graph
package make sure that you download it
into your project when you have this
package installed we need to also
download the sample package so here in
the Shader graph description we have
those samples and this contains
procedural patterns those include a
rectangular grid and a hex grid so make
sure that you import this into your own
project when you're done in the project
tab you are going to find in the assets
samples folder which contains your sub
shaders that we have imported as samples
before we explore those samples we are
going to create a new Shader graph so
I'm going to select my shaders folder
right click create select Shader graph
I'm using urp pipeline so I'm going to
select the only Shader graph I'm going
to call it a grid rectangular
transparent
and I'm going to open this Shader up
okay here is my graph
here in the Shader graph window press
spacebar and either search for grid
and if you don't find anything we will
need to go to samples and open those
folders until you reach the subshooters
we're going to drag the grid topshooter
into our graph and I'm going to maximize
our Shader graph and as you can see here
is our grid node so we can modify the
size and we need to skip it around one
but basically we are controlling the
size of the cells I'm going to set it to
0.95 for now the next parameter that we
have is the tile link we can set it to
four by four basically we are modifying
the number of cells shown or outputted
by our grid node and we can modify the
offset so this allows us to adjust the
position of those grid lines and the
cells if we need to now since we want to
grab the edges or the lines of our grid
rather than the cells we are going to
Output drag the output of the grid to 1
minus node
so now you can see that those white
lines are representing what will be
visible and the black spaces of the
cells will be transparent right now we
need to enable transparency in our
Shader so go to the graph inspector if
you don't see it just press in the top
right corner graph inspector and the
Blackboard we're going to go to the
settings we are going to select the
surface type we're going to select
transparent and now in the fragment
Shader we should see not only the base
color but also the alpha value we're
going to drag the output of the one
minus node to the base color and to the
alpha value and in the main preview you
can right click and select the quad and
you will see that we are not outputting
a grid that is four by four
let's save our Shader click save asset
in the top left corner I'm going to
unmaximize the Shader and I'm going to
go to my shaders folder right click on
the Shader graph that I have created
create and I'm going to select material
okay I'm going to select the scene View
and I'm going to create in the hierarchy
select a 3D object and create a plane
since there is a bit of Z fighting we
are going to select the transform of
this plane make sure that it is set on
zero zero zero and on the y-axis we are
going to rise it by
0.015 so it is on top of our grass plane
and I'm going to drag our Shader graph
material that we have created on this
Lane and as you can see we have our grid
visualization our grid overlay on top of
our grass plane now the problem with
this is that if I select the transform
of the plane and scale it on X we are
going to be stretching of these cells
instead of adding more cells to our grid
so that's what we want to achieve also I
want to point out that if we select our
plane and press shift H we're going to
go to the isolation mode for this plane
if I now go to the scene View and select
the display mode and select the
wireframe we are going to see that
actually our plane is represented by 10
Unity units by 10 unit units so this is
the default scale okay let's reset the
shielding mode to be shaded and let's
press shift age to go out of the
isolation mode for the plane and let's
go back to our Shader to be able to use
our scale properly and to add more cells
when we scale our plane we will need to
go to the Blackboard and here we are
going to add a new Vector to property
using this plus icon let's call it
default
scale
and we are going to set it using the
graph inspector using the node settings
we are going to set the default value to
be 10 by 10. since this is the size of
our plane Indian P units next thing that
we want to do is add another variable of
type color and we are going to call it
well we can leave it as a color this
will be the color of our grid let's set
the default color to be white with full
Alpha although it doesn't really matter
now to be able to modify the size of our
grid we are going to add another Vector
to size
and we are going to leave it for now at
one by one so let's set the default
value to one by one and we are going to
be able to modify the size of the cells
of the grid next we need to add another
parameter of type float and we are going
to call it thickness
and this will be the thickness of our
grid lines we are going to select the
mode to be a slider and we are going to
set the mean value to be 0.01 and we are
going to set the max value to be
0.05 and let's set the default value to
be 0.05
okay so this will allow us to set the
thickness of the grid lines now let's
drag the graph inspector away and we are
going to add a new note so press
spacebar and we are going to type object
because we need to access the scale of
this object we are going to drag it to
the split node because we need to access
only the X and the Z value so R and B so
we are going to drag the R value so x to
the vector 2 x value and we are going to
drag the B values of the Z scale to the
Y of this Vector 2. let's drag it a bit
further so now we have our scale of the
object we are going to drag it the
multiply node and I have already
explained that the default scale of the
object or default size is 10 by 10 so
we're going to multiply the output of
the scale by the default size of our
plane so this will be the 10 by 10 value
now we can use the output of this
multiply node directly onto the grid
tile Link in case we want to always have
the cell size to be one by one but if we
want to be able to modify it we need to
drag the multiply output to another
multiply node and we are going to
multiply this by the size so the vector
one by one right now but we can use it
to multiply the size output of this
previous multiplication so now we can
modify the size of the each cell of our
grid so we are going to drag it to the
tiling of the grid I just want to point
out that we are multiplying this value
by the size but obviously if we set the
size to be 2 by 2 here we are going to
get more cells so let's select the size
and set it to be two by two you're going
to increase the number of cells but in
our grid component we need to set it to
be Point Half to achieve more granular
grid so we could use a divide node here
but it is more performant if we use
multiplication operation since this
Shader will run this code very often so
that's why we are accounting for the
performance using the multiplication
node we are going to set the size back
to 1 by 1. okay so we have our tile link
now we need to use the thickness
parameter from our Blackboard let's drag
it and since I have told you that we
need to have the value around one we are
going to use the one minus node
to subtract the thickness from value 1
and now we can drag the result as the
size of our grid so this will be the
size of the cells and we are going to
thanks that be able to modify the value
or the size of the edges or the lines of
our grid we could of course add one more
parameter for the offset if you need to
modify it now let's go to the fragment
Shader and instead of directly dragging
this result of 1 minus to the base color
we are going to drag this to the
multiplying node and we are going to
multiply this by the color so let's drag
the color from our Blackboard and let's
multiply this Lines by the color and now
we're going to drag the result of this
multiplication to the base color so if
we modify the color we are going to
modify the color of the lines of our
grid okay so this is it for this Shader
let's save this and let's go back to our
scene in case you want to learn more
about cheaters check out the UNT Shader
Bible by jet Ellie it should help you
out now the result is that we are seeing
the grid that contains 10 by 10 cells if
you want to modify it we can go to the
material in the projects Tab and we can
select the thickness and modify the
thickness we can change the color here
and we can also change the size if we
set it to be 2x2 we are going to
obviously have more cells so to apply
this to our grid component we would need
to select it and we are going to select
the grid grid parent and we would need
to set the size to be 0.5 the account
for the more granular grid that's why I
have mentioned that we are multiplying
in the Shader but in the grid cell size
we wouldn't to set the half of the size
to adjust it we are going to leave those
values as one and we are going to change
the material size to be one by one since
those is the size of the prefabs that I
have preferred for the later part of
this tutorial now let's make sure that
we drag our plane to the a grid parent
and let's make sure that both grid and
plane are at position zero zero zero and
let's press play
great so now we have our grid
visualization and we can move our cell
preview or cell prefab around those
cells and we see that it moves just like
we would want it to so the grid
representation is valid I just want to
point out that thanks to creating a grid
parent object and putting the plane and
the grid as the child objects we can
easily move it and you will see that we
can still adjust our placement of the
cell representation to the grids
represented by our Shader so everything
is working if I reset the position of
our grid parent I can also scale the
plane if I scale it by 1.5 we can
experience a problem with selecting the
cell so we need to adjust the plane
position so just give it an offset so
all the position we are going to give
that 0.5 and 0.5 and now again our cell
representation matches what we have
selected on our grid and we can still
select the cells that are outside side
of the grass plane but that are
represented by our grid visualization
plate great in the next video we are
going to start placing objects on our
grid see you there